Guide to the Agur Gilbert Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Agur Gilbert family papers
1839-1919
1839-1885
MS 998
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
Papers of the family of Agur Gilbert, wood turners and toy makers of Derby, Connecticut. Consists of family correspondence, business letters, and account books, primarily for A. Gilbert and Son.
Gilbert, Agur
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Agur Gilbert was born on May 2, 1807, in Huntington, Connecticut. He died on January 23, 1887, in Derby, Connecticut. His wife, Mary Louise Johnson, was born on September 28, 1808, and died on January 24, 1864, in Derby, Connecticut. They were married on February 4, 1830, in Derby, and had five children.
Scope and Contents
Papers of the family of Agur Gilbert, wood turners and toy makers of Derby, Connecticut. Consists of family correspondence, business letters, and account books, primarily for A. Gilbert and Son.
Business; Families; Woodworking industries; Working class; Connecticut; Derby (Conn.) -- History; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Account books; Businessmen; Gilbert, Agur; A. Gilbert & Son
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  These are papers of the Gilbert family who were wood turners and toy makers of Derby, Connecticut. See also the inventory catalog under Gilbert Family Collection, which consisted of these papers, plus those of the Peyton R. Gilbert family (now MS Group No. 699).
  - Maria, Clara, and Kate J. Andrews, daughters of P. B. Andrews: letters to Mary L. Gilbert and Susan Gilbert, wife and daughter of Agur Gilbert, 1854-1870 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Columbia M. (Phelps) Bennett: letters to her cousin, Susan Gilbert, 1852-1857 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - David J. Gilbert, son of Agur Gilbert: letters to his family, 1863-1865 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lewis and Lydia Gilbert: ALS to Agur Gilbert, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mary L. (Mrs. Agur) Gilbert: ALS to Agur Gilbert, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - David B. Rowell: letters to Alfred Gilbert, 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Henrietta E. Wilson: letters to her cousin, Susan Gilbert, and to Susan Gilbert's stepmother, 1867-1869 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fannie (Gilbert) _____, daughter of Lewis and Lydia Gilbert: letters to Agur Gilbert and his son Alfred, 1871-1875, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous family letters, 1862-1872 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Business letters to Agur Gilbert, William F. Gilbert, and A. Gilbert & Sons, 1869-1919, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Account book for day labor, 1844-1878 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Account book, 1854-1884 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ledger, 1858-1885 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Account books, 1839-1883, 1861-1881 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notes on the descendants of Lewis and Sally (Ward) Gilbert, [post-1883] (Box 1, Folder 15)